Guide to the Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Records, 1945-2005 AIS.2006.19A
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Records
1945-2005
1995-2000
ULS Archives & Special Collections
STUDIO for Creative Inquiry
AIS.2006.19A
14.33 Linear Feet (16 boxes and 5 oversized folders)
The Nine Mile Run Greenway Project was a brownfield reclamation project between 1995-2000 in the City of Pittsburgh, Pa. The project was created and coordinated by Reiko Goto, Bob Bingham, and Tim Collins of Carnegie Mellon University's STUDIO for Creative Inquiry. The records contain material that documents the Nine Mile Run area's transformation from a brownfield site to a usable urban space that includes both housing and natural environments.
History
The Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Records consist of planning and outreach materials related to the brownfield redevelopment of the Nine Mile Run area. This stream, which is situated in the City of Pittsburgh, flows into the Monongahela River across from the borough of Homestead. The project lasted between 1995 and 2000 under the direction of Tim Collins and Reiko Goto, who were fellows at Carnegie Mellon University's STUDIO for Creative Inquiry at the time.
Nine Mile Run is a historic stream valley identified by Frederick Law Olmstead, Jr. in 1910 for its beauty as well as its wastewater. By 1928, the valley was selected by influential Pittsburghers for a city park but was subsequently purchased by a steel industry slag disposal firm, the Homestead Steel Company. Between 1930 and 1970 this area was used as a disposal location by Pittsburgh-area mills resulting in a 21-story high pile of slag, a by-product of steel making. The pile covered 238 acres along Nine Mile Run from the Squirrel Hill Tunnel to the Monongahela River shore.
In 1997 the Urban Redevelopment Authority (URA) of the City of Pittsburgh acquired the site from Duquesne Slag, a subsequent owner, and proposed to build 1,200 residential housing units and develop 100 acres of public space. The site's entire surface area was projected to be surrounded by a contiguous public space along the stream from Frick Park to the Monongahela River. This 238 acre acquisition is the largest in history of the Urban Redevelopment Authority and the project included the largest stream restoration in the United States by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers.
The redevelopment of the Nine Mile Run area was a collaborative effort between artists, scientists, engineers, historians, and planners in conjunction with the STUDIO for Creative Inquiry, a research center in the College of Fine Arts at Carnegie Mellon University. The general objective of the project was to develop a transferable model for use in reclaiming other urban brownfield sites.
At the close of the redevelopment process the environment was beginning to show signs of cleaner water. For the first time in 100 years three game fish (smallmouth bass, striped bass, and sauger) were found in the creek along with several other species of minnows and crayfish. The remediation of this area did not end with the project however; in the spring of 2001 the Nine Mile Run Watershed Council was created with the responsibility of conserving Nine Mile Run. The Nine Mile Run Watershed Council consists of both the City of Pittsburgh and upstream community members.
The two major actors in this project were Tim Collins and Reiko Goto. Collins is an artist-research fellow at the STUDIO for Creative Inquiry at Carnegie Mellon University. His academic interests are focused around art and environmental change which can be seen in this project and, more recently, 3 Rivers 2nd Nature, both of which he co-directed with Reiko Goto. Goto's academic interests focus on ecological art projects, which can encompass both redevelopment and installation works.
Scope and Content Notes
The Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Records consist of correspondence, reports, financial records, minutes, outreach materials, journal articles, workshop planning and implementation files, photographic materials, recorded interviews and meetings, moving image recordings of tours and programs, and maps. The material mainly dates between 1995-2000.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Records, 1945-2005, AIS.2006.19A, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 11 series:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Research Data and Reports Collected
Series III. Financial Material
Series IV. Minutes and Agendas
Series V. Outgrowth Projects
Series VI. Outreach Presentations and Programs
Series VII. Project Planning Material
Series VIII. Reference Material
Series IX. Workshops
Series X. Audio-Visual Material
Series XI. Maps
Acquisition Information
Gift of Carnegie Mellon University in 2006.
Related Material
Three Rivers Second Nature Project Records, 1948-2005, AIS.2006.19B, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Hazardous waste site remediation -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Brownfields -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Reclamation of land -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Community development -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Nine Mile Run (Pa.); Parks -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Real estate development -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Factory and trade waste -- Environmental aspects -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Soil pollution -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Water -- Pollution -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Plant reintroduction -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Land use, Urban -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Urban renewal -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Floppy disks; CD-ROMs; Video recordings (physical artifacts); Videocassettes; Audiotapes; Riparian restoration -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Wildlife reintroduction -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Correspondence; Minutes (Administrative records); Maps; Wetland restoration -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social action; Environment; Pittsburgh (Pa.). City Planning Commission; Pennsylvania State University; United States. Army Corps of Engineers. Pittsburgh District; Nine Mile Run Greenway Project (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Gotō, Reiko; Bingham, Bob (Robert C.); Collins, Tim (Timothy M.); United States. Environmental Protection Agency; Allegheny County (Pa.). Health Department; Urban Redevelopment Authority of Pittsburgh; Lyon, Sean; University of Pittsburgh; Carnegie-Mellon University; STUDIO for Creative Inquiry; Summerset at Frick Park (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Allegheny County Sanitary Authority; Carnegie Museum of Natural History; Chester Environmental (Monroeville, Pa.); Pittsburgh (Pa.). Water Department. Laboratory
- Correspondence, 1994-2002; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains correspondence regarding the Nine Mile Run Greenway project. The correspondence is largely general in nature, but includes dialogue from funders and from individuals involved with other greenway or reclamation projects.
  - 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Research Data and Reports Collected, 1945-2005; II.
  This series contains research data and reports collected regarding the Nine Mile Run Greenway project such as reports, studies, and assessments which were used to aid in the planning process of the area's redevelopment.
  - Allegheny County Sanitary Authority, 1945-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carnegie Mellon University, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Carnegie Museum of Natural History, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chester Environmental, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 9-14)
  - City of Pittsburgh Water department Laboratory, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Civil and Environmental Consultants, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cooper, Robertson, and Partners Advanced Technology Systems, Inc., 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Corps of Engineers, Pittsburgh District, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Department of City Planning, City of Pittsburgh, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pensylvania State University, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sean Lyon, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - The STUDIO for Creative Inquiry, 1995-2000 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Swisshelm Park Nine Mile Run Development Committee, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Urban Redevelopment Authority of Pittsburgh, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Other individual reports, 1971-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Financial Material, 1996-2004; III.
  This series contains financial material directly related to the Nine Mile Run project, such as grant applications and budgets.
  - Allegheny County Health Department, Alliance for the Chesapeake Bay, Andropogon Associates Ltd., Anne L. and George H. Clapp Charitable and Educational Trust, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Resources, Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection, 1993-2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Environmental Protection Agency, 1996-2001 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Graham Foundation, Gunk Foundation, Howard Heinz Endowment, 1996-2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - League of Women Voters, National Endowment for the Arts, and National Environmental Education and Training Foundation, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Urban and Community Forestry Advisory Council, Pennsylvania Department of Housing and Urban Development, Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission, Pennsylvania Resources Council, PCA Organizational Grant, 1996-2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Silver Eye Center for Photography, State Water Institute Program, Three Rivers Environmental Awards, and USDA Natural Resources Conservation Service, 1996-2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Minutes and Agendas, 1996-2000; IV.
  This series contains minutes and agendas of the administrators of the Nine Mile Run Greenway project, which documents the evolution of the project from concept to implementation.
  - 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
- Outgrowth Projects, V.
  This series contains information pertaining to two outgrowth projects. The first documents the new housing development called Summerset at Frick Park, a residential neighborhood that was built on top of a slag heap in Nine Mile Run and contains 700 residential housing units. The other project is the Watershed Council which is an organization responsible for the maintenance of the Nine Mile Run Greenway area.
  - Summerset at Frick Park, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Watershed Council Formation, 1997-2002 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Watershed Council, Meeting Agendas, Minutes, and Budgets, 2003-2005 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
- Outreach Presentations and Programs, 1986-2000; VI.
  This series contains material pertaining to outreach presentations and programs designed to get the community invested in the Nine Mile Run Greenway project. Themes included are art exhibition material, Carnegie Mellon University class material, contacts, Nine Mile Run cycling material, press releases and newspaper clippings, public presentations, and Reiko Goto K-12 education outreach program. The latter was created to comply with an agreement the Nine Mile Run Project team had with the Pennsylvania Department of Education which stated that the department would act as a state sponsor and facilitator of the project if a member of the project team would act as a vehicle to train teachers on how to incorporate environmental education into a regular classroom. This educational residency lasted for one year.
  - Art Exhibition Material, 1996-2000 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Carnegie Mellon University Classroom Materials, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Contacts, 1994-2000 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Nine Mile Run Cycling, October 19, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Press Releases and Newspaper Clippings, 1986-1999 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Public Presentations, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reiko Goto K - 12 Education Outreach Program, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Project Planning Material, 1995-2002; VII.
  This series contains material used for project planning, including drafts, plans, and recommendations.
  - Background and Introductory information on Nine Mile Run, 1996-2000 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - "Brownsfields: A New Environmental Frontier," Conference Proceedings, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Community Recommendations for Nine Mile Run, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Environmental Reconstruction Material, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Executive Summaries and Business Plans, 1995-1999 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Frick Watershed Association and Summerset Planning, 1998-2002 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Local Government Proposals, Legislation, and Pittsburgh Regional Parks Master Plan, 1995-2001 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Nine Mile Run Conceptual Alternatives, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Nine Mile Run Rivers Conservation Plan, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
  - Nine Mile Run Watershed Management Plan, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - Nine Mile Run Revised Project Summaries, 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Reference Material, 1951-2001; VIII.
  This series contains reference material used throughout the duration of the project, such as pieces of legislation, journal articles, and bound publications.
  - Legislation, 1966-1998; 1.
    This subseries contains pieces of legislation that were referenced by the administrators of the Nine Mile Run Greenway project. The legislation found here includes serveral levels of government entities.
    - Municipal, County, and State Legislation, 1966-1998 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Federal and Miscellaneous Legislation, 1966-1998 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Articles, 1988-1999; 2.
    This subseries contains loose articles that were referenced by the administrators of the Nine Mile Run Greenway project. The material was predominately pulled from professional journals and consists of photocopies and material printed from online resources.
    - Chronological Articles, 1988-1999 (Box 4, Folder 1-12)
  - Bound Publications, 1951-2001; 3.
    This subseries contains bound publications that were referenced by the administrators of the Nine Mile Run Greenway project. The material is professionally published by either a federal agency or a publication company.
    - "The Miami Conservancy District" By: Arthur Morgan, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "A Sampler of Design Guidelines for Tradiational Neighborhoods" By: UDA Architects, October 14, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - "The Job of the Practicing Planner" By: Albert Solnit, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - "Rapid Bioassessment Protocols for Ise in Streams and Rivers: Benthic Macroinvertebrates and Fish" By: EPA, May 1989 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "Countryside Stewardship Echange in the Chesapeake Bay Region" By: The International Countryside Stewardship Exchange, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Linking the Environment to the New Competitiveness: Strategic Directions for the Pittsburgh Region" By: Sustainable Economic Development Project, Carnegie Mellon University, May 15, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "A Heritage for the 21st Century: Conserving Pennsylvania's Biological Diversity" By: Pennsylvania Biodiversity Technical Committee, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "Bassett Creek Wetland Park: Redevelopment in a Landscape of Wetland Soils" By: University of Minnesota Department of Landscape Architecture and Design Center for American Urban Landscape, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - "Floods, Floodsplains, and Folks" By: National park Service Rivers, Trails, and Conservation Assistance Program, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - "Borough of Wilkinsburg Comprehensive Plan 'Moving Toward the Future'" By: Wilkinsburg Planning Commission, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - "Better Site Deisng: A Handbook for Changing Development Rules in Your Community" By: Center for Watershed Protection, August 1998 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - "Report of the Pennsylvania 21st Century Environment Commission" By: Pennsylvania 21st Century Environment Commission, September 1998 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - "A Watershed Primer for Pennsylvania: A Collection of Essays on Watershed Issues" Edited by: Janette M. Novak and William H. Woodwell Jr., 1999 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - "Seen & Unseen Conference: Collaborative Solutions to Pollution", November 10 - 11, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "A Management Plan for Pitsburgh's Regional Parks" By: ETM Associates, April 14, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "The City of Pittsburgh Master Development Planning in Hazelwood and Oakland: Summary of the Public Design Workshop" By: The Saratoga Associates, May 5, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - "Hazelwood: Making New Connections" By: University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public and International Affairs Campstone Seminar in Economic Development, Policy, and Planning, Spring 2001 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Tree Seed Collection Information Packet" By: Blue Mountain Reclamation Project, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "Water Supply for the Greater Pittsburgh Area: 1988 and Beyond" By: Carnegie Mellon Department of Engineering and Public Policy School of Urban and Public Affairs and the Department of Social and Decision Sciences, December 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Allegheny County Stormwater Management Study: Phase I Report" By: Coopers & Lybrand, April 1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Review and Acceptance Criteria: Waterline and Sewerage Mapping Conversion Project" By: Allegheny County Health Department, Geographic Information Systems Office, and Public Drinking Water and Waste Management Division, May 5, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Stormwater Management: A Review of Municipal Practices and Regulations" By: Department of Environmental Resources Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, April 1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - "Riparian Area Management: Process for Assessing Proper Functioning Condition for Lentic Riparian-Wetland Areas" By: U.S. Department of the Interior, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "Urban Waterways: Public Access and the Public Trust" By: Letitia C. Langord, October 19, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "Girtys Run: A Study in Urban Watershed Management" By: Carnegie Mellon University Environmental Studies Institute, May 8, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - "Nine Mile Run Watershed Rivers Conservation Plan" By: Timothy Collins, David Dzombak, John Rawlings, Ken Tamminga, and Sue Thompson, August 1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - "Ample Opportunity: A Community Dialogue Final Report" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, February 1998 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - "Pittsburgh Main Thoroughfares and the Downtown District" By: Frederick Law Olmsted, February 1911 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - "Parks a part of the Pittsburgh Plan" By: Citizens Committee on City Plan of Pittsburgh, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - "Nine Mile Run: A Study on the Reclamation and Sustainable Redevelopment of a Brownfield Site" By: Carnegie Mellon University Department of Engineering and Public Policy and Department of Social and Decision Sciences, May 1, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - "Montour Run Watershed: Water Quality and Aquatic Life Resources" By: U.S. Army Corps of Engineers Pittsburgh District, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - "Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Community Comment Book for the Commercial Avenue Site" By:Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - "Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Community Comment Book for the Mid-Slag Site" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - "Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Community Comment Book for the Duck Hollow Site" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - "Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Community Comment Book for the Regent Square Gateway Site" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - "Nine Mile Run Greenway Project Community Comment Book for the Lower Frick Park Site" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - "Community Brownfield Guidebook: Assessing and Resolving Environmental Barriers to Redevelopment" By: Nancey Green Leigh and Rhonda Hise, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - "Steel Mill Slag: Leachate Characteristics and Environmental Suitability for Use as a Streambank Protection Material" By: U.S. Army Corps of Engineers Pittsburgh District, March 1989 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - "Phase I Environmental Site Assessment of Nine Mile Run Slag Area" By: Chester Environmental, January 1995 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - "Report on Clean-up Plan for Nine Mile Run Slag Area" By: Urban Redevelopment Authority of Pittsburgh, June 1997 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - "Acid Mile Drainage Control & Treatment" Compiled by: Jeffrey G. Skousen & Paul F. Ziemkiewicz, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - "The Ecology of a City Park" By: William LeRoy Black, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - "Request for Proposal for Services for Jack's Run Sewer Remediation Project" By: Allegheny County Sanitary Authority, May 12, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - "48 Inch Trunk Sewer Modifications in Conjunction with the State Route 28 East Ohio Street Improvement Project" By: Chester Engineers, May 1998 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - "Fried-Reineman Outfall Structure A-66 Modifications" By: Chester Engineers, April 29, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - "The Regionalization Report: An Initial Study on Options for Regionalizing the Management of Sewage Collection within the ALCOSAN Service Area" By: 3 Rivers Wet Weather Inc., January 2002 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - "A Watershed Approach to Urban Runoff: Handbook for Decisionmakers" By: Terrene Institute, March 1996 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - "Montour Run Watershed: A Case for Conservation" By: Montour Valley Alliance, January 2000 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - "Nine Mile Run-Frick Water Shed Public Space Design Team" By: Carnegie Mellon University Studio for Creative Inquiry, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "Slag in the Park: A History of Nine Mile Run" By: Andrew S. McElwaine, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - "Nine Mile Run Watershed Rivers Conservation Plan" By: the City of Pittsburgh, Carnegie Mellon University, Carnegie Museum of Natural History, and Pennsylvania State University, August 1998 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - "Final Recommendations The Nine Mile Run Greenway Project: An Institutional and Economic Plan with Conceptual Design Guidelines" By: Ray Reaves, Stephanie Flom, John Stephen, and Tim Collins, December 1999 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "Reclamation Art" By: Tim Collins and Reiko Goto, Spring 1997 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - "Wetlands for Clean Water: How Wetlands Protect Rivers, Lakes, and Coastal Waters from Pollution" By: The Clean Water Network and Natural Resources Defense Council, April 1997 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - "A Handbook of Constructed Wetlands Volume 1: General Considerations" By: Luise David for the USDA-Natural Resources Conservation Service and the US Environmental Protection Agency-Region III., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "A Handbook for Constructed Wetlands Volume 5: Stormwater" By: Luise David for the USDA-Natural Resources Conservation Service and the US Environmental Protection Agency-Region III., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "Watershed Protection techniques: A Periodic Bulletin on Urban Watershed Restoration and Protection Tools" By: The Center for Watershed Protection, Summer 1995 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - "Watershed Protection techniques: A Periodic Bulletin on Urban Watershed Restoration and Protection Tools" By: The Center for Watershed Protection, Spring 1996 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - "Deisgn Manual: Constructed Wetlands and Aquatic Plant Systems for Municipal Wastewater Treatment" By: EPA, September 1988 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "Riparian Area Management: Procedures for Ecological Site Inventory-with Special Reference to Riparian-Wetland Sites" By: U.S. Department of the Interior Bureau of Land Management (Box 6, Folder 12)